<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Tobby Hagler</title>
    <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com" />
    <updated>2025-07-22T00:42:04-04:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://tobbyhagler.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Sourdough Starter Experiment</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/sourdough-starter-experiment/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/sourdough-starter-experiment/</id>

        <updated>2025-07-22T00:42:04-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>I've finally found some great formulas with sourdough starters that work for me.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I've finally found some great formulas with sourdough starters that work for me.</p>

<p>I've experimented with sourdough starters before, but they ultimately fail because of neglect or impatience. One of my latest sets was no exception. I had two nearly-viable starters after several weeks of feeding (the first was over a month) with still no luck. I tried feeding variations—different ratios, hydration levels, and flour mixes—but only ever saw a slight rise from them. Eventually, I inadvertently killed them by leaving them in the oven with the light on for too long, and they spoiled.</p>
<p>Based on what I've learned about sourdough chemistry (the yeast, the LAB, how feeding and hydration ratios make a difference, here's what finally worked for me. I'm currently growing two amazing starters after only two days.</p>
<h2>Tips for the noobs</h2>
<p>Sourdough requires a kitchen scale. Ratios are based on weight, not volume, so ditch anything that uses the ambiguous "ounce" as a measurement. Convert to grams—this <em>is</em> science, after all, which requires the metric system.</p>
<p>Ratios are expressed as starter-to-flour-to-water, or X:Y:Z. A good practice is to place a clean jar on your scale and tare it to zero. Pour 20 grams of your spent starter into the jar and discard the rest (pro-tip: search for "sourdough discard pancake recipe"). Early days of a starter call for a 1:1:1 ratio: 20 grams of spent starter, 20 grams of water, and 20 grams of flour. Stir well, cover loosely, and let it sit.</p>
<p>Measure the weight of your empty jars beforehand. You'll thank me later.</p>
<p>Another tip is to use an old hair band or a rubber band to mark the level. This way you can see how high it rises over time. Dry erase markers also work well.</p>
<h2>Starter #1: Zymia</h2>
<p>Yeast water + rye and wheat flour.</p>
<p>A week prior, I started some yeast water (originally intended to feed one of the previous starters that was struggling). This consists of a handful of raisins in a jar of filtered water from the fridge and a tablespoon of honey. Stir, shake, and let sit for a week. When it's slightly fizzy when shaken, and before the raisin skins flake off, it's ready. It'll have a slightly sweet, hard cider-like smell to it, and a light, golden-brown color that's not cloudy.</p>
<p>My starter consisted of 30 grams of whole wheat flour and 30 grams of yeast water; a 1:1 starter ratio.</p>
<p>A day later, it rose a little before falling. When I fed it, I didn't discard anything. Instead, I tared the still-full jar and removed it, giving me the weight of the starter once I added the jar's empty weight. In my case, it was around 60 grams of starter. I fed it at a ratio of 1:1:1—60 grams of the spent starter, 60 grams of wheat flour, and 60 grams of yeast water.</p>
<p>The next day, it had nearly doubled in height, with lots of hardy bubbles and a decent dome. That's impressive in only two days.</p>
<p>And it smells so sweet. The familiar sourdough tang is there, along with a cider aroma that's so unique to the yeast water.</p>
<h2>Starter #2: Rhyza</h2>
<p>This one was more traditional. It was a simple 1:1 ratio of 20 grams of rye flour and 10 grams of wheat flour, and 30 grams of filtered water. The first feeding was a 1:1:1 ratio of all 60 grams of the spent starter, 40 grams of rye flour mixed with 20 grams of wheat flour, and 60 grams of filtered water.</p>
<p>At the same time as Zymia's nearly doubled rise, Rhyza had almost tripled in height! I was almost afraid it would expand out of the jar. Thankfully, it reached its peak just before reaching the lid.</p>
<h2>Next steps</h2>
<p>I'll update this blog over time with the progress of these experiments. So far, they're off to great starts.</p>
<p>I will discard and feed them again in the morning, using 1:1:1 of their respective makeup, and re-evaluate in the evening. I will discard all but 20 grams of the starter, so my flour and water will also be 20 grams each.</p>
<p>With the discard of tomorrow evening's feeding (whichever seems the most active), I will make bread. I'll start by feeding the discard with a 1:0.5:0.5 ratio and using the resulting levain to start the bread dough. I estimate that the bread dough will take 8-10 hours, so I'll let it rise overnight. </p>
<p>If it's successful, I'll post the recipe.</p>
<p>Wish me luck!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Grove is Delayed Again</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/the-grove-is-delayed-again/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/the-grove-is-delayed-again/</id>
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2025-07-18T21:47:58-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>...But that's actually a good thing.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>...But that's actually a good thing.</p>

<p>I've been a writer for years, and <em>The Grove of Tau Ceti</em> is my first (finished) novel. I'm really happy with it, too. It took a long time to get here, but I'm now one click away from being a published sci-fi author. I even have physical copies with fantastic cover art by <a href="https://nikwilets.com/">Nik Wilets</a>.</p>
<p>With the help of JB Kish and his <a href="https://www.writingmilestones.com/">Writing Milestones</a> coaching, I could see the path from writer to author. Publication day was <em>initially</em> May 23. With a deadline set—and nothing motivates me more than beating a deadline—we crafted the complete plan I needed to write <em>and publish</em> a novel.</p>
<p>For every milestone reached, I loved the story and its characters even more (except Hector). So when the manuscript came back from my editor, I sent query letters to a few literary agents. You know... because why not?</p>
<p>My stack of rejection letters grew fast. And that's okay. Rejection letters mean you're putting in the work. Right?</p>
<p>Then I got a few of the kind that say, "I love the premise, but it's not what I'm looking for right now." That's still a no, but at least it's an encouraging no. So I kept at it.</p>
<p>And then one day... "Would you mind sending along the next NN pages/chapters?" </p>
<p>As May 23 approached, my manuscript was still under consideration. I pushed the self-publish date to July 25 to leave the door open for traditional publishing possibilities, while keeping a publish-by date on the counter to keep me accountable.</p>
<p>After months of silence, I assumed it wasn't in the stars. It's cool, though. The plan was always to self-publish. Finding a few interested agents who ultimately send rejections still exceeded my expectations when I began working with JB.</p>
<p>And that leads up to why I'm delaying it again. Agents are hellabusy, and sometimes they just can't get back to you for a long time. And I recently got a "still currently considering the project" update, which... [insert Carlton Dance meme]!</p>
<p>I want the best possible publication for <em>The Grove of Tau Ceti</em>, which is why I've decided to postpone the launch again.</p>
<p>My apologies to friends and family who frequently ask, "Is your book out yet?" and I've replied with dates that have come and gone. For now, that answer is simply: "Soon!"</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Announcing Kozy Krampus</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/announcing-kozy-krampus/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/announcing-kozy-krampus/</id>
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2025-07-17T10:53:18-04:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>I'm more excited than a demon with a sack full of kids!</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I'm more excited than a demon with a sack full of kids!</p>

<p>My first published short story will appear in <strong><em data-start="255" data-end="269">Kozy Krampus</em></strong>, an anthology of 29 delightfully twisted tales featuring the horned holiday menace himself. The collection drops late September, just in time to curl up with a mug of something warm and a healthy fear of hooves on the rooftop.</p>
<p>So drop what you're doing and go <a href="https://firebirdcreative.myshopify.com/products/kozy-krampus" title="Pre-order Kozy Krampus" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pre-order</a> now! Or don’t. That’s up to you. But remember: Krampus thinks disobedient children taste the best.</p>
<hr>
<p>Mark Teppo and Frances Lu-Pai Ippolito, eds., <em data-start="381" data-end="395">Kozy Krampus</em> (Portland, OR: Underland Press, 2025).</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
