<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Tobby Hagler</title>
    <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com" />
    <updated>2025-12-27T15:33:16-05:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://tobbyhagler.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Latest Sourdough Loaf</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/latest-sourdough-loaf/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/latest-sourdough-loaf/</id>
        <media:content url="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/IMG_5866-2.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Sourdough"/>

        <updated>2025-12-20T16:26:26-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/IMG_5866-2.jpeg" alt="" />
                    I just took this loaf out of the oven. I've almost got&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/IMG_5866-2.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <div class="gallery-wrapper"><div class="gallery"  data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="3">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/gallery/IMG_5866.jpeg" data-size="2644x3522"><img loading="lazy" src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/gallery/IMG_5866-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="Close-up view of a sourdough loaf's ear" width="768" height="1023"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/gallery/IMG_5871.jpeg" data-size="3176x2382"><img loading="lazy" src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/gallery/IMG_5871-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="Slide view of a sourdough small lamé marks" width="768" height="576"></a></figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/gallery/IMG_5872.jpeg" data-size="2638x2638"><img loading="lazy" src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/15/gallery/IMG_5872-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="Top view of a sourdough loaf's ear and lamé cuts" width="768" height="768"></a></figure>
</div></div>
<p>I just took this loaf out of the oven. I've almost got the timing down, but not quite there, yet. I think it needed 2-3 more minutes on the second half, after taking the lid off the Dutch oven.</p>
<p>I'm starting to get a handle on the lamé leaves; the ear is decent, but I never seem to get the angle just right. I think next time, I'll soak the lamé knife in ice water before scoring it.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>What Revision Actually Feels Like</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/what-revision-actually-feels-like/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/what-revision-actually-feels-like/</id>
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2025-11-10T13:08:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Surprisingly, revisions turned out to be one of my favorite parts of writing *The Grove of Tau Ceti*. It was the moment of "ugh, my draft sucks" to "oh, maybe this thing has some life inside it, yet."</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Surprisingly, revisions turned out to be one of my favorite parts of writing *The Grove of Tau Ceti*. It was the moment of "ugh, my draft sucks" to "oh, maybe this thing has some life inside it, yet."</p>

<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []"><span class="K6pdKd wtBS9"><span class="vqseUe">Terry Pratchett once (and often) said, "The first draft is just you telling yourself the story." And he was absolutely correct.</span></span></p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Revision is the act of opening the machine you built and discovering the screws you thought were decorative are load-bearing. And that the most critical moments aren't actually all that important. With <em data-start="422" data-end="446">The Grove of Tau Ceti,</em> the hard part was the first draft: that sprint to the finish line, the calendar looming on the wall, the “don’t break the chain” word counts.</p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Once I knew (<em>really</em> knew) the story, I needed others to read it and give me feedback -- beta readers to whom I cannot extend a large enough "thank you!" to. Because of them, I could see all the plot holes, the developmental flaws, the good parts and the really terrible ones.</p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">What surprised me is that revisions became one of my favorite parts of making this book. There’s a moment, the shift from “ugh, this draft is mush” to “hol up… there’s a heartbeat under here.” It’s addictive.</p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">The story starts talking back. Characters sharpen and begin to take over. A scene that used to limp suddenly stands upright and says, “You meant to write <em data-start="1088" data-end="1095">this.</em>” Revision is when the book proves it actually wants to live.</p>
<h3 data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Characters misbehaving turned out to be the biggest signal that needed strengthening</h3>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">V didn't have enough agency in the beginning. I had this idea of where I wanted the story to go, but V had other ideas. Revising the story gave me the chance to actually listen to her and let her make her own decisions -- decisions that shaped the story and led to its only logical conclusion.</p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Parker slipping into self-loathing (early first drafts were very "<span data-huuid="10433081068981173336">woe is me"</span>) wasn’t a choice he would make. It was a mistake <strong data-start="1680" data-end="1685">I</strong> made when drafting fast. I had to restore his swagger, make sure he remembered he once called himself "the most dangerous human in Tau Ceti," and then <em>act like it</em>.</p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Rowan needed to shine earlier; his technical prowess and guilt over a past career-limiting incident needed to be clearer. Hawthorne was too guarded early on, and the lack of any vulnerability made her difficult to appreciate. <em>Demeter</em>'s “voice” evolved from a passive computer system to that of a true character. The captain was way too casual and commanded no actual authority. Revisions allowed me to sprinkle in notes of humanity and to fix details, revealing the soul behind every archetypal portrayal.</p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">Revision is making sure the people in a story don’t drift into two-dimensional cardboard cutouts. This is the moment to let them really come alive on the page, to let them become real.</p>
<h3 data-pm-slice="0 0 []">And then...</h3>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">...then it's off to the editor. That's the nail-biting part: what will my editor tell me, and how bad will it be...?</p>
<p data-pm-slice="0 0 []">o_O</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Notes From a Bad Bake</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/notes-from-a-bad-bake/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/notes-from-a-bad-bake/</id>
            <category term="Sourdough"/>

        <updated>2025-11-05T19:24:00-05:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <p data-start="621" data-end="974">Sourdough is applied chemistry, but I am very bad at chemistry. Every baker has a file labeled “Well… that didn’t go according to plan.” Mine is a three-ring binder.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p data-start="621" data-end="974">Sourdough is applied chemistry, but I am very bad at chemistry. Every baker has a file labeled “Well… that didn’t go according to plan.” Mine is a three-ring binder.</p>

<p data-start="621" data-end="974">Sometimes the starter is sleepy. Sometimes the weather is being passive-aggressive. Sometimes my brain insists that 90 percent hydration is a personality trait. A “bad bake” usually starts as good intentions plus one tiny decision that seemed brilliant until it wasn’t.</p>
<p data-start="976" data-end="1355">I'm still learning a ton about baking with sourdough. An autolyse dough rise is important <em>most of the time</em>. Hydration percentages account for additional ingredients (especially wet ones). Enriched dough doesn't play like artisan dough. There's a lot to learn.</p>
<p data-start="976" data-end="1355">But here’s perhaps the most valuable part I’ve had to learn: <em>pivoting is a baking skill</em>.</p>
<ul>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Weak dough?
<ul>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Pan loaf it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Overproofed?
<ul>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Chill it, reshape it, and reset expectations.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Too sticky to shape?
<ul>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Make focaccia.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Overhandled?
<ul>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Dinner rolls.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Dough tearing like tissue paper?
<ul>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Increase rest time and pretend that was always the plan.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">If it has become goop that refuses to let go of your fingers?
<ul>
<li data-start="976" data-end="1355">Sorry, it wasn't meant to be, and either feed it like a starter or dump it into the trash. </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Most mistakes become something edible if you stop arguing with physics and let the loaf tell you what its options are.</p>
<p data-start="1357" data-end="1753">I've had some interesting bakes that were rescues. There was the loaf that spread into a lazy pancake on the counter until I scooped it into a cast-iron skillet and baked it into accidentally perfect focaccia bread. Or the underproofed dough that refused to relax, so I divided it into small rolls and let surface tension do the heavy lifting. (Flattered dough shapes rise higher.)</p>
<p data-start="1755" data-end="2150">I say this at work all the time (though I originally stole it from the Internet): "Good judgment is the result of experience; Experience is the result of bad judgment."</p>
<p data-start="1755" data-end="2150">Here’s a baking corollary: <em>a bake isn't “bad” if it teaches you something, and especially not if it feeds people.</em></p>
<p data-start="1755" data-end="2150">You adjust, you try again, and you stack tiny lessons: wetter isn’t always better, impatience tastes dense, dough likes rest, and the oven forgives a lot. Besides, bread is a living thing. Some days it’s a cooperative friend. Other days, it’s a necromancer with opinions. You learn to work with both.</p>
<h3>Pivot Menu: Full Panic-Button Playbook</h3>
<p><strong>If the dough is too sticky to shape:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Wet hands, not dry flour; this prevents gummy layers.</li>
<li>Do an extra coil fold for structure,</li>
<li>Switch to focaccia or pan loaf mode.</li>
<li>Cold rest 20–30 min to tighten gluten.</li>
<li>Scrape, don’t wrestle. The scraper always wins.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If the dough is tight and tears easily:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Mandatory rest. Gluten needs a moment.</li>
<li>Perform gentler, fewer folds.</li>
<li>Increase hydration a tiny bit next time.</li>
<li>Make rolls, and let surface tension do all the work.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If it’s overproofed and collapsing:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Chill it to slow the yeast down.</li>
<li>Very gentle reshape with minimal degassing.</li>
<li>Proof shorter the second time (watch, don’t time).</li>
<li>Accept the baguette-but-wider aesthetic.</li>
<li>French toast solves morale issues.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If it’s underproofed and stubbornly small:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Warm spot, covered, 15-minute check-ins.</li>
<li>Coil fold to wake up the gluten.</li>
<li>Be patient, gas buildup takes time.</li>
<li>Rebrand as “rustic, dense, European artisan vibes.”</li>
<li>This is a good time to practice your lame scoring techniques.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If the dough spread like a pancake:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Skillet bread to the rescue.</li>
<li>Sheet pan focaccia as Plan C.</li>
<li>Tell people it’s flatbread “on purpose.”</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If shaping has gone feral:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Smaller divisions = easier tension.</li>
<li>Bench knife practice time.</li>
<li>Pretend you invented a new shape. Make knots out of smaller pieces.</li>
<li>Everything looks artisanal if you dust it with flour.</li>
<li>Pro-tip: using stencils while dusting with flour makes it look cool when baked.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If the crust looks great but the inside is gluey:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Bake longer next time. It wasn’t done.</li>
<li>Low-and-slow finish, if it’s salvageable.</li>
<li>Garlic butter forgives all sins.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If the dough has proofed for too long:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Treat it like an early active starter. </li>
<li>Feed it some flour until it becomes handleable again.
<ul>
<li>Note: This <em>will</em> make it dry, once it autolyses.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>This may be the opportunity to practice bassinage hydration.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If you forgot salt:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Garlic butter forgives this, too.</li>
<li>Serve with soup. No one ever complains about plain bread with soup.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>If it tastes fine but looks tragic:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Close your eyes and take another bite.</li>
<li>Butter makes it prettier.</li>
<li>Bread isn’t a beauty pageant. Instagram doesn’t need to know <em>everything</em>.</li>
</ul>
<h3>The One Real Rule</h3>
<p>Pivot early. Pivot creatively. Pivot without shame.<br>Just pivot!</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Reading Dough With Your Hands</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/reading-dough-with-your-hands/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/reading-dough-with-your-hands/</id>
        <media:content url="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/IMG_5934-Medium.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Sourdough"/>

        <updated>2025-10-30T18:27:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/IMG_5934-Medium.jpeg" alt="Sourdough kolache dough rising in a bowl, done with folds." />
                    <p>Dough obeys biochemistry and physics, not calendars. Yeast ferments at the speed the environment allows. Gluten organizes as you move it. Proofing is a sensory process: your hands receive real-time data that the schedule can’t provide.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/IMG_5934-Medium.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Sourdough kolache dough rising in a bowl, done with folds." /></p>
                <p>Dough obeys biochemistry and physics, not calendars. Yeast ferments at the speed the environment allows. Gluten organizes as you move it. Proofing is a sensory process: your hands receive real-time data that the schedule can’t provide.</p>

<p data-start="558" data-end="1089">I’m making kolaches today. The dough started soft and buttery because fats coat and lubricate gluten-forming proteins, slowing their ability to link up. As I mixed and switched to coil folds (pick up gently, stretch using only gravity as tension, fold it over itself a few times, then a final gentle tuck), those long gluten molecules began aligning into a network.</p>
<p data-start="558" data-end="1089">You can feel its status and progress just by handling it.</p>
<figure class="post__image post__image--right"><img loading="lazy" src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/IMG_5934-Medium-2.jpeg" alt="Sourdough kolache dough rising in a bowl, done with folds." width="640" height="640" sizes="(min-width: 760px) 660px, calc(93.18vw - 30px)" srcset="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/responsive/IMG_5934-Medium-2-xs.jpeg 320w ,https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/responsive/IMG_5934-Medium-2-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/responsive/IMG_5934-Medium-2-md.jpeg 768w ,https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/24/responsive/IMG_5934-Medium-2-xl.jpeg 1024w">
<figcaption>Sourdough kolache dough rising in a bowl, done with folds.</figcaption>
</figure>
<p data-start="558" data-end="1089">When it stretches before tearing, it means gluten strands are bonding and creating elasticity. When it tears or feels mushy, the protein matrix isn’t fully crosslinked yet, or it’s overwhelmed by fat and needs a bit longer to relax.</p>
<p data-start="1091" data-end="1499">Warm dough, especially early in the proofing process, can be hard to judge. It's soft, and you're not sure if it's getting stronger or falling apart. A short cold proof can help with getting to know the dough better.</p>
<p data-start="1091" data-end="1499">Cold proofing slows yeast activity because temperature affects metabolic rate. (Microbes are creatures of vibes.) While the yeast chills out, enzymes snip starch into sugars, giving the yeast fresh food when things warm back up. When the dough returns to room temperature and suddenly feels smoother and springier? That’s gluten continuing to strengthen even while “nothing” appeared to be happening.</p>
<p data-start="1501" data-end="1927">Work it for a bit longer. See how it feels. Stop folding when the dough has enough structure to handle gas expansion. If it pushes back against your hands, that’s elasticity saying, “Yo dawg, I’m all good now.” If it slumps, extensibility is winning, and you can help gluten realign with a gentle coil fold or a cardinal stretch-and-fold. When it’s cohesive, warm, and slightly proud of itself... it has gas retention + surface tension + good fermentation... step away. It's on autopilot now.</p>
<h3 data-start="1501" data-end="1927">What Your Hands Are Asking (and the Dough's Answers)</h3>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th><strong>Sensation</strong></th>
<th><strong>What’s Really Happening</strong></th>
<th><strong>What You Do</strong></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Glue-sticky, clings aggressively</td>
<td>Gluten not yet aligned; starches still releasing</td>
<td>Fold or brief rest (gluten relaxes into order)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tacky like a Post-it</td>
<td>Gluten network forming; dough holds tension</td>
<td>Keep going gently</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Smooth, stretchy, holds shape</td>
<td>Strong gluten + balanced hydration</td>
<td>Let it rise undisturbed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Tears easily, feels rough</td>
<td>Overworked gluten tightening or underdeveloped structure</td>
<td>Rest longer; wet hands if needed</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Dent springs back slowly</td>
<td>Balanced elasticity + gas inside</td>
<td>On track. Stop touching it.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A Note on Keeping Two Projects Alive</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/a-note-on-keeping-two-projects-alive/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/a-note-on-keeping-two-projects-alive/</id>
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2025-10-25T17:37:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    People sometimes ask how I juggle multiple writing projects, and the answer&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p data-start="314" data-end="664">People sometimes ask how I juggle multiple writing projects, and the answer is, "badly, but with commitment." I’ve learned that when one story is being stubborn, the best thing I can do is let it sulk in a corner until it comes to its senses and decides to let me work it again. It turns out jealousy and FOMO are powerful creative motivators.</p>
<p data-start="666" data-end="1057">Keeping at least two things alive at once keeps me out of the existential gooey-center of “I must make progress on the 'One Big Thing™' or I am failing at life somehow.” Instead, I can rotate projects like a lazy susan of narrative chaos. If characters from my latest novel aren't cooperating, I can go talk to the goblins. If the goblins are quiet (they rarely are quiet, but they do shut me out frequently), I can work on a flash fiction piece for a contest or an open call with a specific prompt.</p>
<p data-start="1059" data-end="1107">So, what’s currently breathing in the ole brainpan?</p>
<ul data-start="1109" data-end="1590">
<li data-start="1109" data-end="1227">
<p data-start="1111" data-end="1227"><strong><em>The Grove</em> sequel</strong><br data-start="1131" data-end="1134">Most of the crew is back, and the stakes are galactically existential. Because of course they are.</p>
</li>
<li data-start="1228" data-end="1332">
<p data-start="1230" data-end="1332"><strong><em>Frankie and the Goblin King</em></strong><br data-start="1261" data-end="1264">Frankie’s leg is fine, but his patience with the deposed goblin king who inhabits one? Contested even on the best of days.</p>
</li>
<li data-start="1333" data-end="1461">
<p data-start="1335" data-end="1461"><strong data-start="1335" data-end="1373">A cluster of short stories + flash</strong><br data-start="1373" data-end="1376">They’re out there in the world trying to get adopted by various lit mags. Wish them luck.</p>
</li>
<li data-start="1462" data-end="1590">
<p data-start="1464" data-end="1590"><em><strong data-start="1464" data-end="1514">Station and Gary</strong></em><br data-start="1514" data-end="1517">Station built Gary because it was lonely. But Gary is an asshole and now Station has two problems.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p data-start="1592" data-end="1850">Keeping multiple projects alive isn’t multitasking; it’s survival. When one story is stuck in cold fermentation, another one usually starts to rise. And I don’t need everything to bake at once. I just need to make sure nothing dies in the back of the mental fridge.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Query: Current Level of &#x27;Over It&#x27;</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/query-current-level-of-over-it/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/query-current-level-of-over-it/</id>
        <media:content url="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/23/Ginger-over-it.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Dogs"/>

        <updated>2025-10-23T15:38:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/23/Ginger-over-it.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Nothing says it more clearly than a dog who is over it.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/23/Ginger-over-it.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Nothing says it more clearly than a dog who is over it.</p>
<div class="gallery-wrapper gallery-wrapper--full"><div class="gallery" data-is-empty="false" data-translation="Add images" data-columns="2">
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/23/gallery/Ginger-over-it.jpeg" data-size="640x480"><img loading="lazy" src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/23/gallery/Ginger-over-it-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="Ginger hides her face in a purple pillow, underneath a navy blue blanket" width="640" height="480"></a>
<figcaption>Ginger writes to inform you that she is over it. Honk, shoo, and good day!</figcaption>
</figure>
<figure class="gallery__item"><a href="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/23/gallery/Declan-on-clouds.jpeg" data-size="480x640"><img loading="lazy" src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/23/gallery/Declan-on-clouds-thumbnail.jpeg" alt="Declan resting on two white pillows" width="480" height="640"></a>
<figcaption>Declan dreams on floating clouds.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Grove of Tau Ceti releases tonight</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/the-grove-of-tau-ceti-releases-tonight/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/the-grove-of-tau-ceti-releases-tonight/</id>
        <media:content url="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/front-cover-med.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2025-10-22T22:13:02-04:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/front-cover-med.jpeg" alt="Book cover of The Grove of Tau Ceti" />
                    <p>I’m thrilled to share that <em data-start="356" data-end="379">The Grove of Tau Ceti</em> has officially launched!</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/front-cover-med.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Book cover of The Grove of Tau Ceti" /></p>
                <p>I’m thrilled to share that <em data-start="356" data-end="379">The Grove of Tau Ceti</em> has officially launched!</p>

<p>This marks the end of a long and surreal journey — from drafting the first chapter beside a quiet Carolina pond to holding the finished book in my hands.</p>
<p>The novel is now available in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Grove-Tau-Ceti-Tobby-Hagler/dp/B0FWJ4KWFG/">paperback</a> and <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Grove-Tau-Ceti-Tobby-Hagler/dp/B0FX6Y2X77/">Kindle</a> on Amazon, with additional distributors coming soon. Other ebook formats will follow in <strong data-start="726" data-end="742">late January</strong>.</p>
<p>You can learn more at the official website: <a href="https://thegroveoftauceti.com/">thegroveoftauceti.com</a></p>
<figure class="post__image"><a href="https://thegroveoftauceti.com/"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/front-cover-large.jpeg" alt="" width="828" height="1280" sizes="(min-width: 760px) 660px, calc(93.18vw - 30px)" srcset="https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/responsive/front-cover-large-xs.jpeg 320w ,https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/responsive/front-cover-large-sm.jpeg 480w ,https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/responsive/front-cover-large-md.jpeg 768w ,https://tobbyhagler.com/media/posts/13/responsive/front-cover-large-xl.jpeg 1024w"></figure></a></p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Writing as Maintenance, Not Inspiration</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/writing-as-maintenance-not-inspiration/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/writing-as-maintenance-not-inspiration/</id>
            <category term="Writing"/>

        <updated>2025-10-20T17:55:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <p data-start="226" data-end="636">I love inspiration. It’s loud and dramatic and shows up with a fresh sack of confidence like, “Yay! We’re geniuses today.”</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p data-start="226" data-end="636">I love inspiration. It’s loud and dramatic and shows up with a fresh sack of confidence like, “Yay! We’re geniuses today.”</p>

<p data-start="226" data-end="636"><em>But…</em> if I waited on inspiration to actually write regularly, I’d maybe have three paragraphs a month and <em>a lot</em> of very tidy notebooks. Most of the work happens in the boring middle place, when I’m not sure what I’m doing, but I show up anyway. Because here’s the truth that took me way too long to internalize:</p>
<h2 data-start="638" data-end="748">Your Muse will <em>not</em> make house calls</h2>
<p data-start="638" data-end="748">If you want to find her, you have to put on real pants and go look for her. Like an adult, or something. <em>Lame</em>.</p>
<p data-start="750" data-end="1047">Maintenance is the part of writing that keeps the creative engine from seizing up. It’s not glamorous, and it doesn’t feel like “Art” with a capital A, but it’s the thing that makes art possible. Think less “lightning strike” or "glitter bomb!" and more “oil change,” or "tire rotation." The point isn’t perfection. The point is motion. Keep the lanes moving at all costs.</p>
<p data-start="1049" data-end="1176">So here’s a <strong data-start="1061" data-end="1094">Writing Maintenance Checklist</strong> for days when your brain has the creative horsepower of wet cardboard (apologies for the automotive metaphors I'm about to butcher all to Hell):</p>
<p data-start="1178" data-end="1200"><strong data-start="1178" data-end="1200">Mechanical Checks</strong></p>
<ul>
<li data-start="1203" data-end="1274">Open the document you’ve been avoiding. (<strong>Yes</strong>, that counts as progress.)</li>
<li data-start="1277" data-end="1311">Fix one ugly sentence. Just one. The others get prettier as a result, but you can still fix the next-nasty one later.</li>
<li data-start="1314" data-end="1389">Read yesterday’s work out loud and circle the spots that make you cringe. There are also tools that read your work aloud; though, don't spend too much time finding the "right" voice (they all kinda suck).</li>
<li data-start="1392" data-end="1455">Name the problem. If you can diagnose it, you can fix it later.</li>
</ul>
<p data-start="1457" data-end="1473"><strong data-start="1457" data-end="1473">Fuel System</strong></p>
<ul>
<li data-start="1476" data-end="1588">Refill your idea tank.
<ul>
<li data-start="1476" data-end="1588">Read a page of something good. Watch a scene you admire.</li>
<li data-start="1476" data-end="1588">Take <em data-start="1569" data-end="1578">exactly</em> one note.</li>
<li data-start="1476" data-end="1588">Honestly (and <em>yes,</em> I have admitted this to Laura): Period pieces on BritBox are <strong>excellent</strong> for this (the Keira Knightley <em>Pride and Prejudice</em> or the 2008 <em>Sense &amp; Sensibility</em>) are the perfect way to watch three-act story structure unfold.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="1591" data-end="1646">Write a question about your latest piece. Don’t answer it yet. It will answer itself when you're done and struggle with "what's wrong with my story?!"</li>
</ul>
<p><strong data-start="1648" data-end="1670">Alignment &amp; Tires</strong></p>
<ul>
<li data-start="1673" data-end="1768">Move something from Point A to Point B.
<ul>
<li data-start="1673" data-end="1768">A character goal.</li>
<li data-start="1673" data-end="1768">A plot beat.</li>
<li data-start="1673" data-end="1768">A metaphor.</li>
<li data-start="1673" data-end="1768">A comma.</li>
<li data-start="1673" data-end="1768"><em>Let the em dashes live, screw the haters!</em></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="1771" data-end="1818">Re-confirm where the scene is supposed to land. And if it doesn't deserve to live, euthanise it lovingly.</li>
</ul>
<p data-start="1820" data-end="1842"><strong data-start="1820" data-end="1842">Preventative Care</strong></p>
<ul>
<li data-start="1845" data-end="1871">Stop before you hate it.</li>
<li data-start="1874" data-end="1914">Leave yourself a runway into tomorrow.</li>
<li data-start="1917" data-end="1979">Celebrate the tune-up.
<ul>
<li data-start="1917" data-end="1979">Future-you will notice the smooth ride.</li>
<li data-start="1917" data-end="1979">Clean writing is something you can continue living within.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p data-start="1981" data-end="2256">Maintenance writing doesn’t feel heroic. It feels like sweeping the floor. But a swept floor is a space where something can happen. Creativity likes clear paths; it can't stand obstacles, and it <em>abhors</em> debt. It loves momentum. And it desperately needs it when we show up, muttering all the while, “Fine, but I’m not happy about this.”</p>
<p data-start="2258" data-end="2489">That’s the trick. Do the small things that keep the machine humming. And when inspiration <em data-start="2352" data-end="2361">finally</em> sticks her head in the door, she doesn’t have to shout over the sound of a stalled engine. She can just hop in and hit the gas.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Why I Like Cold Fermentation</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/why-i-like-cold-fermentation/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/why-i-like-cold-fermentation/</id>
            <category term="Sourdough"/>

        <updated>2025-10-15T16:55:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    Cold fermentation is basically giving the dough a long nap in the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p data-start="218" data-end="670">Cold fermentation is basically giving the dough a long nap in the fridge while the microbes quietly work out their chemistry assignments. It slows everything down, evens out the yeast-versus-bacteria chaos, and lets flavor develop on its own timeline. In practical terms: you mix, you fold, you tuck it in, and then (this is clutch!) you stop hovering. The dough doesn’t need your motivational speeches. It just needs time in the dark, where it can work on itself and become something richer, with more depth.</p>
<h3 data-start="1992" data-end="2048">Some Science From Inside the Fridge</h3>
<ul>
<li data-start="2051" data-end="2116">Cooler temps favor <strong data-start="2070" data-end="2082">bacteria </strong>-- specifically, <em>Lactic acid bacteria (LAB</em>) -- which deepen acidity and flavor.</li>
<li data-start="2119" data-end="2193"><strong data-start="2119" data-end="2130">Enzymes</strong> break down starch into sugars, giving yeast something to eat over time.
<ul>
<li data-start="2119" data-end="2193">Amylase breaks down flour starches into sugars for yeast and bacteria fuel (too much of this and you get hooch, btw).</li>
<li data-start="2119" data-end="2193">Proteases snip gluten proteins into smaller pieces, making the dough relax.</li>
<li data-start="2119" data-end="2193">Maltase and Invertase (yeast enzymes) break down sugars for microbial energy. Scientifically speaking: carbs go in, bubbles come out.</li>
<li data-start="2119" data-end="2193">There are some others that I always forget about.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li data-start="2196" data-end="2253">Gluten continues <strong data-start="2213" data-end="2230">strengthening</strong> even without kneading.</li>
<li data-start="2256" data-end="2313">Overproofing is <strong data-start="2272" data-end="2287">less likely</strong> because yeast slows down. The yeast and LAB balance is easier to maintain.</li>
<li data-start="2256" data-end="2313">And <strong>the best part</strong>: the dough becomes easier to shape thanks to that chilled elasticity.</li>
</ul>
<p data-start="2390" data-end="2495">All that complexity is earned by basically doing nothing, which is my favorite thing to do. But it requires patience. Time bends, stretches, and ignores linear causality, especially in the presence of carbs.</p>
<h3 data-start="218" data-end="670">Cold Fermentation, Patience, and Resilience</h3>
<p data-start="672" data-end="1112">Writing a novel (or any piece of fiction, really) is very similar. I drafted <em data-start="735" data-end="758">The Grove of Tau Ceti</em> like I was on a timer, convinced speed equaled progress. In fact, I kept a calendar with word counts and deadlines, and I refused to miss those targets. That's the <em>only</em> way I got the first draft written at all.</p>
<p data-start="672" data-end="1112"><em>But</em> after the first big rise came the chill phase: the months of querying, the rejections, the no-responses, the “This isn’t quite right for our list” that all feel like your starter refusing to dome. The book's publication wasn’t broken. It was fermenting. Slowly. Very slowly. Microbial geologic-time slowly.</p>
<p data-start="1475" data-end="1796">Cold fermentation reminds me that waiting isn’t the absence of progress. Things develop in the quiet. The kitchen may look still, the bowl may look unchanged, but chemistry is in session. So when I put a dough to rest (or put a draft in a drawer), I try to remember: the rise doesn’t need permission, it just needs time.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On Starting Things Before You’re Ready</title>
        <author>
            <name>Tobby Hagler</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/on-starting-things-before-youre-ready/"/>
        <id>https://tobbyhagler.com/posts/on-starting-things-before-youre-ready/</id>
            <category term="Writing"/>
            <category term="Sourdough"/>

        <updated>2025-10-10T18:57:00-04:00</updated>
            <summary type="html">
                <![CDATA[
                    <p>Stop sharpening pencils. That wears them down faster than writing with them.</p>

                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Stop sharpening pencils. That wears them down faster than writing with them.</p>

<p data-start="159" data-end="711">There’s this myth that preparedness is a gate you pass through, like once you’ve read enough articles or watched enough bakers coil-fold dough on YouTube (watching slap folds is my favorite, but it's never as easy as they make it look), a bell dings, and you’re licensed to begin.</p>
<p data-start="159" data-end="711">In real life, readiness is usually something you discover halfway through messing something up. My first loaf didn’t care that I’d spent a week “researching hydration percentages.” It just sat there like a beige swamp creature until the oven convinced it to commit to being bread. <em>Starting</em> is what creates the readiness, not the other way around.</p>
<p data-start="713" data-end="1180">It's the same with writing. We can outline ourselves into a paralysis spiral, convinced one more note will finally unlock the perfect first sentence. Meanwhile, the draft is over there, coughing loudly, like “Hey, I exist when you actually type something.”</p>
<p data-start="713" data-end="1180">You don’t learn the shape of a story by thinking about it in the abstract. You learn it by letting sentences wobble around until they find their center of gravity. Premature perfection is a hobby for machines, not humans. And machines can't write or </p>
<h3 data-start="1182" data-end="1468">So: start before you think you're qualified.</h3>
<p data-start="1182" data-end="1468">Bake when your starter still smells edgy. Write when the keyboard is stiff, or the pencil is still dull. Your Muse will not make house calls. You have to go find her. Begin while you're still slightly confused and underproofed. Just keep going until the words begin to rise.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
